gopal balachandra now joining in thank
you so much for taking time out now when
we're taking a look at the combined
ratio this quarter we seen an uptick
sequentially so what has led to this
rise in the
quarter so that's a great start uh if
you are to ask us um so again I think as
you rightly mentioned uh the combined
ratios for this quarter uh should at
roughly at about 10 14.5% at an
aggregate level and we did get impact Ed
by a set of catastrophic events in this
quarter we had floods in Gujarat we had
floods in telengana we had the North
Indian floods now we one was to kind of
factor in for all of these flood events
and if we were to exclude the impact of
these cat losses then the reported
combin of 104.5 comes down to about 10
12.6% uh and this number when you look
at it on an year on year basis for a
similar quarter there is actually a
marginal Improvement of roughly about 2%
in so far as a combined is concerned uh
but I think uh I would kind of say that
our business is more long-term and
therefore you should always end up
looking at the numbers ideally on annual
cycles and hence to that extent
quarterly there could be uh aberration
in terms of the business mix in terms of
the loss experiences etc etc but what we
stand committed is what we also put out
as a part of the anist call uh which we
did on Friday uh we stand committed to
the number that we spoke about to the
market which is to get to an ex exit a
combined ratio of
101.5 uh so at this point of time we are
not making any changes to that and hence
to that action that is what we will be
largely driving it
at right I also wanted to talk about you
know the fact that while your growth has
remained strong across the segments and
you also gain market share in fi25 so
far overall the industry growth has
declined in the month of September do
you see any headwinds in growth at a
macro level
yeah so I think that's that's a good
that's a good question because I think
uh the beauty of the general insurance
business that we are that we are at and
particularly for companies which are
into
multi-line um that's exactly how things
play out I think you will obviously see
at different points of time possibly
maybe some bit of competitive intensity
play out maybe to some extent uh demand
getting uh possibly impacted uh but the
good news is I think there are always
opportunities that arise or result from
some of the other segments that we are
into and that is what we kind of stay
invested in terms of seizing uh
opportunities from an i lombar
standpoint and that's exactly as you
rightly said for us in that sense if you
look at across the key segments that we
generally talk about which is motor
health and the commercial lines put
together uh you absolutely right I think
we did have an outperformance when you
look at uh whether it is motor in the
aggregate or whether you look at even
Health as a category on both those those
lines of businesses I think we have been
able to have a significant
outperformance relative to the industry
growth on the commercial lines and
specifically in the context of fire I
think in line with what we've been
talking to the market at this point of
time we are seeing maybe elevated levels
of competitive intensity and to that
extent at least specifically in the
context of fire we have largely
maintained our market share in that
segment whether you look at it on a
quarter two or whether you look at it
even on a halfly basis however given the
in structure thrust that the government
is making on projects Logistics etc etc
the rest of the lines of commercial
businesses for is Lombard has actually
seen a positive growth momentum when you
look at it in the context of engineering
Marine cargo liability now all those
businesses have kind of done well for
us all right and you had also mentioned
the rising competition so going ahead
can we see any price hikes or any
product launches that you have in the
pipeline for certain categories that
will help alleviate
this let's start with commercial lines
for example right so when I said that uh
the market has been competitive in fire
insurance as a line of business now this
is a segment which is high on exposures
because these are large properties large
risks that we underrate and therefore to
that extent there is an element of
reinsurance that pretty much every
company uh works on and re insurers also
are providers of capital and therefore
when they see pricing possibly dropping
a lot they would not necessarily be
making available free reinsurance
capacity now all this conversations is
something that will start to happen
towards the beginning of the renewal
cycle which is generally towards quarter
4 of this financial year so and and just
to kind of refresh if you were to go
back three four years back that is
exactly what happened when the
reinsurers did see stress in pricing
from a market perspective they clearly
indicated that in case if companies
wants to Avail reinsurance capacity then
they will have to kind of increase
prices so possibly uh given that at this
point of time there is an elevated
levels of uh price competitiveness maybe
at the time of the renewal cycle things
will start to kind of look upon in terms
of increase in pricing but in that
context when you look at it for IC
Lombard given that we are largely trying
to stay disciplined in terms of risk
selection I think hopefully the terms of
reinsurance renewals that we are likely
to expect should generally be positive
so hence to your point there could be
some kind of a price action when you
look at it in the context of commercial
lines when it comes to health I think as
you rightly mentioned for us the newly
launched solution which is Elevate I
think that has been kind of received
very well across multiple stakeholders
and that's the reason why I said our
market share is now at about 3.5 3.6% in
that range right and during the recent
me the government announced the
exemption of GST on health insurance as
well below 5 lakhs uh we may also see
exemp exemption on health insurance
premiums for senior citizens as well
what's your take on this and how is it
that you see this benefiting your
company I think I'll just put this in
the context so at this point of time I
think let's wait for uh some of this uh
uh crystallizations to kind of get
fructified so we will so at this point
so until then I think obviously we will
not want to necessarily comment on as to
what is the change to what extent on
which segments of businesses could this
be made applicable etc etc but having
said that I think if you look at it in
the context of the opportunity that one
sees on health and leave aside the uh
large part of the population which is
the vulnerable section of the society
who are largely kind of getting covered
under the government sponsored Mass
health program so if you to keep that
aside and the rest of the insurance if
you were to see the extent of
penetration it is significantly lower
and that is where the opportunity lies
and from an insurance regulator
standpoint I think the regulator has
been rightly kind of positioning the
opportunity to make sure that as as
companies we are kind of working towards
uh increasing penetration now any
exemption any uh reduction of tax rates
in so far as an individual consumer is
concerned obviously we will that is very
that's an absolute welcome because in so
far as their out of pocket uh payment is
concerned is definitely a positive when
it comes to the insurance companies
obviously we will have to do our
evaluations and see as to whether is
there really an impact consequent to the
exemptions to whatever extent that that
proposals could come through I think we
will evaluate and take an action
appropriate there too but in general I
think the whole thought process in terms
of why the exemption to what category
Etc is all largely to drive penetration
on the one hand and equally to make sure
that insurance is becoming far far and
more affordable when it comes to
Consumers all right and on the
investment front what is your
sensitivity towards the rate cut cycle
which may begin soon what kind of uh uh
you know how investors should be into
that answer the first part uh see the
beauty of the business for us is uh I
think the entire investment book uh is a
proprietary book uh it completely
belongs to shareholders and therefore to
that extent the investment calls that we
end up taking can be uh for a longer
period and that is exactly how I lomard
has always historically positioned our
books uh and if you were to look at
across various uh various rate cycles
and and at times when the interest rates
have stayed elevated as in elevated as
in when the interest rates have been
higher at those times obviously we have
kind of gone significantly long in terms
of the duration of the book and just to
kind of explain at this point of time we
running a duration of close to about
5.41 years so hence to that extent at
least in so far as the position of the
book is concerned I think we are rightly
paused depending on as and when maybe
rate cut cycle could kind of come
through we did go long over the last
couple of years specifically taking
advantage of the high
interest rate regime because it kind of
augur well not only in terms of higher
interest approvals for us but at the
same time I think it a possibly also
helps us uh in terms of any realization
of gains as when the rate cycle where to
get fructified at so we are kind of
rightly posed in terms of the
opportunity that one sees there uh and
that is why if you see our overall
unrealized gains that we have on the
overall investment book that's roughly
at about 25 billion rupees of which
close to about 16 billion is on the
equity side and roughly about 8 to 9
billion rupes is on the uh fiction C
portfolio uh and we will obviously have
a lot more depending on how the rate
rate cut cycle plays out to your second
point on the investment leverage I think
again as I keep saying I think our
businesses are more longer term in
nature and therefore to that extent you
always have to end up looking at any of
the metzes over a long-term Horizon and
in that context now when you look at the
investment leverage which for maybe
quarter two or let's say on a half
yearly basis stands at about 3 91 in
general to the market we have talked
about maintaining The Leverage at
roughly at about four
times right so great to have you on the
show then uh thank you so much uh uh
gopal for taking the time out and
speaking with us
today there comes a time when your heart
calls for you to arise plant your feet
solid into the ground decide your own
limits and then break right through them
become something
more it's my time to rise